<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>8-Bit Hustler</title>
  <id>http://tiandavis.com</id>
  <link href="http://tiandavis.com" />
  <link href="http://tiandavis.com/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <updated>2014-06-08T02:52:34-04:00</updated>
  <rights>Copyright 2014, Tian Davis</rights>
  <author>
    <name>Tian Davis</name>
  </author>
  
    <entry>
      <title>JavaScript and The Monomyth</title>
      <link href="http://tiandavis.com/posts/javascript-and-the-monomyth" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/new-chart-of-history.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The Hero's Journey&quot; alt=&quot;The Hero's Journey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his seminal work, &quot;The Hero with a Thousand Faces&quot;, Joseph Campbell put forth the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hero_with_a_Thousand_Faces&quot;&gt;The Monomyth&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is based on the observation that a common pattern exists beneath the narrative elements of most great myths, regardless of their origin or time of creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, all of mankind's myriad myths are but variations of a single great story. This is the monomyth and is most commonly expressed as a hero's journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this journey, the hero begins in the ordinary world, and receives a call to enter an unknown world of strange powers and events. The hero who accepts the call to enter this strange world must face tasks and trials, either alone or with assistance. In the most intense versions of the narrative, the hero must survive a severe challenge, often with help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the hero survives, he may achieve a great gift or &quot;boon.&quot; The hero must then decide whether to return to the ordinary world with this boon. If the hero does decide to return, he or she often faces challenges on the return journey. If the hero returns successfully, the boon or gift may be used to improve the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Monomyth has three arcs: The Departure, The Initiation and The Return. Each arc has several sub arcs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to stop here for a second because I want you to think about your favorite movie. Is it Frank Herbert's Dune? Or Star Wars? Or The Highlander? Is it Braveheart? Or The Matrix? Or maybe even Quentin Tarantino's Django?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all but variations of a single story. JavaScript is no different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of JavaScript and how it came to be is an amazing story. But the people who gave it life and continue to nurture its growth are but actors in a greater story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in the telling of this story, you and I, experience the psychic unity of mankind. A unity that binds us to the craft. JavaScript is the hero here. This is its journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The 17 Stages of the Monomyth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Departure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a monomyth, the hero begins in the ordinary world, and receives a call to enter an unknown world of strange powers and events. The hero who accepts the call to enter this strange world must face tasks and trials, either alone or with assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectively, mankind faced the beginnings of the strangest and most powerful of worlds it had ever created - The Internet. So sets the stage for our hero and the birth of a language...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Call to Adventure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the Call to Adventure, the hero begins in a mundane situation of normality from which some information is received that acts as a call to head off into the unknown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early April 1995, Brendan Eich is recruited to Netscape with the promise of &quot;doing Scheme&quot; in the browser. Netscape recruited him because he could hack quickly and in part because he had some language chops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explained Brendan, &quot;I was 'that guy', not in any brag-worthy sense, just the only person who was in the position to do the deed, with (barely) enough skills to pull it off.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brendan goes on to explain, &quot;Many hackers could have done a better job with more time, or perhaps a better job had they been in my shoes. Who knows? But no one at Netscape could have, and the opportunity was there and then&quot;, Brendan on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2783060&quot;&gt;Origins of JavaScript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opportunity was there and then and he took it. What a lot of folks don't know is Brendan worked for Netscape's founder's previous company Silicon Graphics Incorporated (SGI); That's how he was recruited to Netscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SGI was a high performance computer designer/manufacturer. Think Alienware for business. SGI are also the folks that wrote and open sourced the C++ standard template library (STL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STL was an early standard library for C++ without which you'd have to write your own base data structures like lists, hashes, queues and the like. In his own words, his experience at SGI made him a &quot;C/Unix fanboy&quot;. &quot;I knew the C grammer by heart&quot;, he would later explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things seldom go according to plan and little did he know both Scheme and C would play heavy on his design of JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Refusal of the Call&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Often when the call is given, the future hero first refuses to heed it. This may be from a sense of duty or obligation, fear, insecurity, a sense of inadequacy, or any of a range of reasons that work to hold the person in his or her current circumstances.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brendan never did put Scheme in the browser. Instead, he created a new language called JavaScript. As he remembers it, &quot;[t]he diktat from upper engineering management was that the language &lt;a href=&quot;https://brendaneich.com/2008/04/popularity/&quot;&gt;must 'look like Java'&lt;/a&gt;.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After partnering with Sun Microsystems, the creators of Java, Netscape management was firm that whatever language created should be &quot;Java's kid brother&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to bring Java to the Netscape browser in the form of Java Applets. Then use JavaScript to tie everything together. The Netscape/Sun deal was to make Java for &quot;professional&quot; developers and JavaScript, well, for everyone else. The express goal was to embed that programming language in the source HTML of Netscape Navigator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management only cared about two things. First, the new language look like Java. Finally, the new language have objects without classes. In their mind, a dumbed down version of Java. In Brendan's mind, challenge accepted...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a subversive agenda, Brendan borrowed closures and first-class functions from Scheme. Then, he borrowed the concept of prototypical inheritance from Self. Whereas Scheme was a dialect of Lisp, Self was a dialect of Smalltalk. Finally, he borrowed the look-and-feel of the language from C/C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In class-based object oriented languages, classes define the properties and behaviors of objects. Object instances are then particular manifestations of a class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Self, however, one makes a copy of an existing object and then adds additional specific properties and behaviors. Code which uses the existing objects are not changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These would form the necessary ingredients for creating JavaScript, but it would take an act of God to birth the language into existence. In the software development industry, we call these acts of god a release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Supernatural Aid&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Once the hero has committed to the quest, consciously or unconsciously, his guide and magical helper appears or becomes known. More often than not, this supernatural mentor will present the hero with one or more talismans or artifacts that will aid them later in their quest.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netscape 2.0 Beta's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jwz.org/gruntle/nscpdorm.html&quot;&gt;extremely tight release schedule of March 1996&lt;/a&gt; forced Brendan to complete the first version of JavaScript in only &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jwz.org/blog/2010/10/every-day-i-learn-something-new-and-stupid/#comment-1048&quot;&gt;ten days&lt;/a&gt;. Management at Netscape was sure Microsoft was gunning for them, after turning down a low ball offer to buy Netscape earlier that year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's the old saying, &quot;Just because you're paranoid doesn't mean they aren't after you.&quot; In this case, Microsoft was out for Netscape and the killer was to be VBScript in Internet Explorer. Things were about to get real - real fast...!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though still the market leader in web browsers, Netscape speed up its release of Netscape 2.0. I like to think of that release as a crucible. In went Brendan Eich, his experiences with Scheme, Self, Java and C; his marching orders for the language to &quot;look like Java&quot; and &quot;have objects without classes&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those things were the raw &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Japanese_swordsmithing#Metallurgy&quot;&gt;Tamahagane&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through those inhomogeneous mixtures of concepts and directives a finer language would reveal itself. Through the crucible, out came what would be one of the most popular programming languages in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once the soot was removed and the steel polished, JavaScript was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Crossing the Threshold&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the point where the person actually crosses into the field of adventure, leaving the known limits of his or her world and venturing into an unknown and dangerous realm where the rules and limits are not known.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Fall of 1996, Brendan &lt;a href=&quot;https://brendaneich.com/2011/06/new-javascript-engine-module-owner/&quot;&gt;rewrote the JavaScript language&lt;/a&gt; and built the first-ever JavaScript engine. This engine is code named SpiderMonkey and is later released as open source. JavaScript is finally decoupled from the Netscape browser. JavaScript is standardized as ECMA-262 specification called EMCAScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft implements JavaScript for the first time in Internet Explorer 3.0 in August 1996 - Here, it is called JScript. As explained by JavaScript guru Douglas Crockford in his talk titled The JavaScript Programming Language on YUI Theater,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Microsoft] did not want to deal with Sun about the trademark issue, and so they called their implementation JScript. A lot of people think that JScript and JavaScript are different but similar languages. That's not the case. They are just different names for the same language, and the reason the names are different was to get around trademark issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tsdr.uspto.gov/#caseNumber=75026640&amp;amp;caseType=SERIAL_NO&amp;amp;searchType=statusSearch&quot;&gt;&quot;JavaScript&quot; is a trademark of Oracle Corporation&lt;/a&gt;. It is used under license for technology invented and implemented by Netscape Communications and current entities such as the Mozilla Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time in 1997, a fork of SpiderMonkey is developed at Netscape called &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhino_(JavaScript_engine)&quot;&gt;Rhino&lt;/a&gt;. Where SpiderMokey is written in C, Rhino is developed entirely in Java. At the time, Netscape was planning to produce a version of Netscape Navigator written fully in Java and so it needed an implementation of JavaScript written in Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course Rhino could be embedded into any Java application to provide scripting to end users. Say for example you wanted to build a version of Excel running on top the JVM. And say your wanted to provide scripting capabilities in Excel similar to VBA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would you do it? Well, you could use Rhino and voila your Excel-ish application can provide users with scripting abilities written in JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here on out, JavaScript would be free from confinement to any one single browser. Yet future funding of this open source language was still confined to a handful of proprietary, nominally closed source companies. Something had to give...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gods must have seen the irony because it wouldn't be too long before this situation came to a head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Belly of the Whale&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The belly of the whale represents the final separation from the hero's known world and self. By entering this stage, the person shows willingness to undergo a metamorphosis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early 1998, Netscape along with Brendan found the Mozilla Project. Named after the original code name of the Netscape Navigator browser which is a blending of &quot;Mosaic and Godzilla&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mozilla Project is meant to manage open-source contributions to SpiderMonkey and  Netscape's Mozilla Suite - an open source browser and email client combined. A small group of Netscape employees were tasked with coordination of the new community. Brendan serves as the group's first chief architect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That same year whispers begin that AOL plans to buyout Netscape and shutdown the Netscape browser. A year later in 1999, AOL does buy Netscape. However, the shutdown doesn't come for another four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in July 2003, AOL officially shuts down its Netscape browser unit. That same month, Brendan helped create the Mozilla Foundation as the legal steward the Mozilla Project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after, the Mozilla Project deprecated the Mozilla Suite in favor of creating independent applications for web browsing and email. The Firefox web browser and the Thunderbird email client were born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way, the SpiderMonkey JavaScript Engine found a new home in Mozilla's Firefox web browser. Later in 2005, Brendan becomes the CTO of the for-profit arm of the Mozilla Foundation - the Mozilla Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript was now on the golden path. In addition to not being tied to a single browser, now it would be funded, indefinitely by a foundation dedicated to its future and the future of us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Initiation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most intense versions of the narrative, the hero must survive a severe challenge, often with help. If the hero survives, he may achieve a great gift or &quot;boon.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Java applets failed, JavaScript became the de-facto language of the Web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a growing number of browser vendors, the future of JavaScript laid on the foundation of inconsistent implementations and frustrated developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, with a little help, the promise of JavaScript everywhere had a very real chance to succeed. But, it wasn't easy...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Road of Trials&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The road of trials is a series of tests, tasks, or ordeals that the person must undergo to begin the transformation. Often the person fails one or more of these tests, which often occur in threes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luke Skywalker had his Lightsaber training with Obi-Wan Kanobi. Neo his sparring with Morpheus. They had it easy...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had they faced learning JavaScript, in what was our stone age, they would have failed like so many of us. Between 2003 and 2005, three major factors played a pivotal role for JavaScript as a development language and they didn't work in its favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the number of web browser vendors was growing. Then the Document Object Model (DOM) was a mess. Finally, JavaScript organization was an improbability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as web browser vendors, there was Netscape of course, but then there was also Internet Explorer (Windows and Mac OSX). There was the burgeoning Firefox and growing in popularity was Safari and Opera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each implemented the spec in their own slightly different vision. Some were worse than others - I'm looking at you Microsoft. The implementation of some JavaScript objects were radically different across browser vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some browser vendors didn't implement certain objects at all or implemented them with another name and slightly different responsibility. Those were the best cases. At the worse end, you had browsers like Internet Explorer (IE) which implemented its own proprietary extensions and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What that meant is if you wrote your code against IE first, your goose was pretty much cooked. A lot of enterprise companies realized this far far to late and carte blanche told developers to write code against IE and IE only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most developers either didn't know the self-defeating result of such policies or simply didn't care. For the craftsman, however, it would be years until they could stand against such tyranny with both competence and a following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, supporting as many browsers as possible would continue to be an uphill battle. Later, we would find that each browsers Document Object Model (DOM) implementation was just as bad - if not worse...!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://ejohn.org/blog/the-dom-is-a-mess/&quot;&gt;DOM&lt;/a&gt; was a also mess. CSS selectors were inconsistent. DOM modification from JavaScript was inconsistent. Event management was downright agonizing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the most widely used DOM method - getElementById - returned inconsistent results from every browser. But it wasn't just that method, nearly every DOM method was broken in some way, in some browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moral of the story was if there's a DOM method, there's probably a problem with it somewhere, in some capacity. All of this was compounded by the growing popularity of JavaScript and its frenzied, almost barbarian integration to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_HTML&quot;&gt;Dynamic HTML&lt;/a&gt; (DHTML) techniques had grown in popularity. It wasn't long before developers took to JavaScript like a fat kid to cake. JavaScript was all over there place like spaghetti with a toddler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time most of us joined a team, JavaScript was scattered inline throughout HTML. There were monstrous JavaScript files. Sometime so many they would make you dizzy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I once showed up to a client to find JavaScript stored in database tables and spewed out to the user like a bad burrito. Those were the times when you prayed to the Gods. It was monstrous to the point of culpability. JavaScript organization was without reason. More crime than art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many browsers, the DOM was a mess and JavaScript organization was a thing unheard of. Yet, all this insanity was sort of, well - beautiful. Beautiful because it showed developers identified with JavaScript. It showed a willingness to push the language further than anyone thought possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was this willingness to go beyond that would form a fundamental cornerstone of the JavaScript community. And with such a large elephant, we began to eat it piece by delicious piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Meeting with the Goddess&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the point when the person experiences a love that has the power and significance of the all-powerful, all encompassing, unconditional love that a fortunate infant may experience with his or her mother. This is a very important step in the process and is often represented by the person finding the other person that he or she loves most completely.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;January 2006, John Resig released &lt;a href=&quot;http://ejohn.org/blog/bar-camp-nyc/&quot;&gt;jQuery at BarCamp NYC&lt;/a&gt;. jQuery opens the door for JavaScript to run consistently in every browser. Up until now, no one had taken on the challenge to reconciled JavaScript behavior across disparate browser vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The promise was simple - write your JavaScript against jQuery and your code was guaranteed to run in every browser. Now, it is common place to use jQuery. But, back then, not many people stopped to wonder what it could be to have JavaScript just work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprising when you think about it because most code was server-side. In fact, ajax techniques had just barely started to become known. All this meant was folks simply didn't care about the frontend. All that changed with jQuery. Because of jQuery developers started to wake up and start noticing JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, clearly John is not a Goddess and neither is he a God. It funny because The Matrix had the Oracle and the Oracle was able to see a person's destiny. Well, I felt like John is our Oracle and he saw not just what JavaScript was, but what it could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of John and jQuery, collectively, we realized the dream of cross-browser development. We had finally normalized JavaScript development and laid a solid foundation for innovation. During this time, John taught us about the DOM in all its shabby self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-Obtrusive JavaScript (no inline JavaScript) started to become a very real possibility. JavaScript code organization would still remain a mess for quite some time unfortunately. But, at least it worked as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wouldn't be long before jQuery became synonymous with cross-browser JavaScript development, but it didn't get there without challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Temptation away from the true path&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this step, the hero faces those temptations, often of a physical or pleasurable nature, that may lead him or her to abandon or stray from his or her quest.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don't have to wonder where JavaScript would be without jQuery. For me, the answer is clear...Nowhere! Without cross-browser compatibility, JavaScript would have been of very little use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for but a moment, I dare you to imagine a world without jQuery. What if I told you that was almost the case? It was...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With jQuery and the dream of cross-browser development in its infancy, many developers were courted by and tempted away by other JavaScript frameworks like MooTools, Prototype and ExtJS. So began The Framework Wars...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, all three brought classical object oriented programming to JavaScript. Genius really...But its hard to say whether the larger development community were ready for these concepts at the frontend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn't like today where domain logic is steadily moving frontward. Back then, domain logic was firmly planted server-side and most developers were struggling with object oriented concepts even there, much less in a prototypical environment. For these early frameworks, classical OOP turned to be a deadly weakness in spite of its overall strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, most JavaScript consumers at the time really had no idea the history of the language or how powerful it could be. To them it was a scripting language and &quot;everyone&quot; knew you didn't do heavy lifting with those things. So hitting them with classes and design patterns right off the bat was like opening a first date with, &quot;So...I met this amazing wedding planner.&quot; It was simply too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not bad in and of itself - just too much too fast. Besides, most developers didn't come for code organization and design patterns, they came for the plugins - calendars, accordion menus and the like were all the rage...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, jQuery looked really promising but the plugins were ugly. MooTools had some really beautiful plugins, but the Community believed you should only use one JavaScript framework and they weren't budging. ExtJS simply felt too heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one knows how the war started. As with all wars, the issue was about assets and who would go on to own the dollar ($) alias. It seems silly now, but folks risked mixing multiple frameworks to use widgets they liked from each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers were used to mixing widget libraries from the DHTML days. Now, they were just happy these widgets would work in multiple browsers. But as with things too good to be true, there was a catch...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Atonement with the Father&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In this step the person must confront and be initiated by whatever holds the ultimate power in his or her life. In many myths and stories this is the father, or a father figure who has life and death power. This is the center point of the journey. All the previous steps have been moving into this place, all that follow will move out from it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around May 2008, almost two years after the initial release of jQuery, The Framework Wars peaked. But with developers firmly in either camp, this war would be won with converts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As integral as the dollar ($) alias was, no framework wanted to change their use of the dollar ($) alias just to suit &quot;some other framework&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made it difficult to mix and match components from different frameworks without them clobbering each other. This was the turning point for the future of JavaScript and its proliferation to the masses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came jQuery.noConflict()...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using jQuery.noConfict() John and the jQuery team allowed developers to continue to use jQuery's dollar ($) sign while still allowing other frameworks to work properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What John Resig and the jQuery Core Team realized was that people used the dollar ($) alias for &lt;a href=&quot;http://tiandavis.com/posts/rails-3-and-the-jquery-effect/&quot;&gt;efficiency not identity&lt;/a&gt;. So why not let other frameworks use the $ alias and give jQuery developers the best of both worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, jQuery developers didn't have to choose efficiency over flexibility. While the other frameworks pandered, &quot;One Framework to Rule Them ALL&quot;, jQuery introduced jQuery.noConflict(), played it's hand and moved aside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After trying jQuery, many developers never went back to either MooTools, Prototype or ExtJS. Instead, they opted to rewrite their most favorite plugins in jQuery. What came next was the Golden Age of jQuery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Apotheosis (becoming god-like)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This step is a god-like phase where the hero earns a period of rest, peace and fulfillment before the hero begins the return.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May 2008, Douglas Crockford published his seminal book &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/JavaScript-Good-Parts-Douglas-Crockford/dp/0596517742&quot;&gt;JavaScript: The Good Parts&lt;/a&gt;&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Crockford identified the abundance of good ideas that make JavaScript an outstanding object-oriented programming language-ideas such as functions, loose typing, dynamic objects, and an expressive object literal notation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later that year, in September 2008, Microsoft switches out its own &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jquery.com/2008/09/28/jquery-microsoft-nokia/&quot;&gt;AJAX library for jQuery&lt;/a&gt; and ships jQuery with Visual Studio. Two years later, in March 2011, the popular Ruby web framework, Ruby on Rails, switched out &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dhh/statuses/45923430608023552&quot;&gt;Prototype for jQuery&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As JavaScript had become the de-facto programming language of the web, jQuery had become the de-facto JavaScript normalization framework of the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Ultimate Boon&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ultimate boon is the achievement of the goal of the quest. It is what the person went on the journey to get. All the previous steps serve to prepare and purify the person for this step, since in many myths the boon is something transcendent like the elixir of life itself, or a plant that supplies immortality, or the holy grail.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jQuery opened cross-browser JavaScript development to all developers. Later libraries either made jQuery the foundation for interacting with the browser or implemented a compatible (sometimes identical) API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript was becoming a language for &quot;real&quot; developers. Consistent behavior in every browser was our version of the elixir of life...It was our holy grail and led to many innovations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JSON or &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON&quot;&gt;JavaScript Object Notation&lt;/a&gt; became the standard for transmitting objects between a server and web application using Ajax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brainchild of Douglas Crockford, JSON uses human-readable text to transmit data objects consisting of attribute–value pairs. It is used primarily to transmit data between a server and web application and steadily became an alternative to XML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libraries like &lt;a href=&quot;http://raphaeljs.com/&quot;&gt;Raphael&lt;/a&gt; show us we never needed flash for beautiful interactive graphics. It also showed us what a commitment to cross-browser consistently can yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raphael is a cross-browser JavaScript library that draws Vector graphics for web sites. It will use SVG for most browsers, but will use VML for older versions of Internet Explorer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the DOM remained a mess, JavaScript normalization libraries like jQuery shield us from its quirks. However, JavaScript code organization remained messy for some time. Yet, as innovation grew, so grew the potential for sane JavaScript with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Return&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hero must then decide whether to return to the ordinary world with this boon. If the hero does decide to return, he or she often faces challenges on the return journey. If the hero returns successfully, the boon or gift may be used to improve the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Refusal of the Return&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Having found bliss and enlightenment in the other world, the hero may not want to return to the ordinary world to bestow the boon onto his fellow man.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John leaves the Mozilla Corporation, and work on jQuery, to join the Khan Academy. The project is left in the hands of a core group of developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript is now cross-browser, but code organization is still a mess and often turns into spaghetti code. Lighter weight versions of jQuery, optimized for mobile devices show up like Zepto, but they only support IE10+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something else was brewing under the covers. Something very few people saw coming. The very way some started to write JavaScript changed entirely. The age of the Designer Language began...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Magic Flight&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sometimes the hero must escape with the boon, if it is something that the gods have been jealously guarding. It can be just as adventurous and dangerous returning from the journey as it was to go on it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://techoctave.com/c7/posts/90-designer-languages&quot;&gt;Designer Language&lt;/a&gt; is a programming language created to avoid the perceived shortcomings of an existing language, usually by creating a superset of the existing language by modifying syntax or modifying programming constructs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2009, Jeremy Ashkenas, quietly committed &lt;a href=&quot;http://coffeescript.org/&quot;&gt;CoffeeScript&lt;/a&gt; to the JavaScript world. CoffeeScript was a programming language that &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Source-to-source_compiler&quot;&gt;transcompiled&lt;/a&gt; to JavaScript. It was also the first designer language to bring back the concept of class based programming to JavaScript. In a short two years, CoffeeScript managed to influence legions of developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, CoffeeScript made its way to Brendan Eich - The Creator of JavaScript - inevitably influencing the future of the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired by Ruby, Python and Haskell, CoffeeScript went on to become the default JavaScript language in the popular Ruby on Rails web framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With those results, CoffeeScript is (arguably), the most successful designer language ever released. But that was just the beginning of JavaScript's designer languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Web Toolkit or GWT attempted to transpile Java to JavaScript (Oh how the mighty had fallen). Dart, GWT's predecessor, was Google's attempt to make GWT more like JavaScript. Effectively, Dart was Google's answer to CoffeeScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Microsoft would attempt to answer CoffeeScript with there own language called TypeScript. Both TypeScript and Dart would attempt to bring static typing to JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClosureScript transpiled Closure, a dialect of LISP written for the JVM, to JavaScript. Objective-J, though short lived, had identical syntax to Objective-C and transpiled to JavaScript as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's interesting is most designer languages still allowed you to use all your favorite frontend frameworks like jQuery. Though some like GWT and Objective-J do not because they provide their own underlying framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Times were changing rapidly. The grassroots investment in JavaScript by the development community didn't go unnoticed. JavaScript became the &lt;a href=&quot;http://redmonk.com/dberkholz/2014/05/02/github-language-trends-and-the-fragmenting-landscape/&quot;&gt;most popular language used on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Rescue from Without&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just as the hero may need guides and assistants to set out on the quest, oftentimes he or she must have powerful guides and rescuers to bring them back to everyday life, especially if the person has been wounded or weakened by the experience.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apple.com/hotnews/thoughts-on-flash/&quot;&gt;Apple dropped support for Flash&lt;/a&gt; on its new iPhone in favor of more open standards like HTML5, CSS and JavaScript. In subsequent years, &lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.adobe.com/message/4580870&quot;&gt;Adobe itself would drop support for Flash&lt;/a&gt; on mobile devices all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft drops support for IE6 as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.modern.ie/en-us/ie6countdown&quot;&gt;countdown&lt;/a&gt; to the death of IE6 continued. jQuery would later create a project fork that drops support for IE6 as to decrease the libraries bloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Crossing of the Return Threshold&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The trick in returning is to retain the wisdom gained on the quest, to integrate that wisdom into a human life, and then maybe figure out how to share the wisdom with the rest of the world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.stevensanderson.com/2012/08/01/rich-javascript-applications-the-seven-frameworks-throne-of-js-2012/&quot;&gt;Micro MVC libraries&lt;/a&gt; arise to offer JavaScript code organization along with jQuery integration. Some of those libraries include Backbone, KnockOut, Spine and JavaScriptMVC (CanJS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backbone, written by the creator of CoffeeScript - Jeremy Ashkenas, is a JavaScript library with a RESTful JSON interface and is based on the model–view–presenter (MVP) design pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backbone is lightweight and its only hard dependency is Underscore - also written by Jeremy. Underscore is a JavaScript library which provides utility functions for common programming tasks and delegates to native browser implementations when present or a compatible version when absent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KnockOut, Spine and JavaScriptMVC (CanJS) all aimed to organize JavaScript as Backbone did, but with each its own unique approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time, Google open sources its V8 engine. Like its ancestor, SpiderMonkey, V8 is an open source JavaScript engine. V8 is the JavaScript engine behind Google's Chrome web browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, projects like &lt;a href=&quot;http://nodejs.org/&quot;&gt;NodeJS&lt;/a&gt; use the V8 engine to turn JavaScript into a legitimate server-side language. This was the first server-side JavaScript runtime. But it was the first to realize a thriving ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Node gave us real-time, two-way connections using the HTML5 WebSocket protocol. The primary method to take advantage of HTML5 WebSockets was through &lt;a href=&quot;http://socket.io/&quot;&gt;Socket.IO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socket.IO is a JavaScript library for realtime web applications. It has two parts: a client-side library that runs in the browser, and a server-side library for NodeJS. Both components have a nearly identical API. Like NodeJS, it is event-driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socket.IO primarily uses the HTML5 WebSocket protocol, but if needed can fallback on multiple other methods, such as Adobe Flash sockets, JSONP polling, and AJAX long polling, while providing the same interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socket.IO normalized WebSockets across disparate browsers. Using Socket.IO, you can guarantee WebSocket consistently across all the major browsers. Socket.IO is to HTML5 WebSockets as jQuery was to JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's interesting about this is as the HTML5 spec grew nearer to completion, micro libraries grew to fill the consistency gap as browser vendors normalized functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript begins to show up in microcontrollers like Raspberry PI and Arduino. JavaScript starts showing up in flight drones like the AR Drone and Parrot as its programming language. Even object databases like MongoDB store objects as JSON.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was starting to become clear to everyone that JavaScript was now simply everywhere...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Master of Two Worlds&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mastering two worlds is usually represented by a transcendental hero like Jesus or Buddha. The person has become comfortable and competent in both the inner and outer worlds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of NodeJS, it was now possible to use JavaScript throughout the entire application stack. JavaScript had mastered the server-side and the frontend as well. Core business logic moved from the server to the frontend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the server becomes just another API which is consumed by various frontends. So the Single Page Application (SPA) arose. Now the debate isn't which server-side web application framework do I use, instead many developers ask what frontend framework do I use to organize my code?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frontend MVC frameworks like Ember and Angular arise to answer that question. &lt;a href=&quot;http://emberjs.com/&quot;&gt;Ember&lt;/a&gt; provides an opinionated framework with coverage for common uses cases and is unobstructive with jQuery integration. Ember is the Rails of JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://angularjs.org/&quot;&gt;Angular&lt;/a&gt; has elements of inline JavaScript called directives. Most common scenarios must be implemented by the developer. But its not really inline JavaScript, just custom Angular properties embedded in HTML. If jQuery is not present in your script path, Angular falls back to its own implementation of a subset of jQuery Google calls jQLite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major competition to both Ember and Angular is the micro MVC library Backbone. Most developers combine Ember for code organization with jQuery for DOM manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some developers mix in a designer language like CoffeeScript, TypeScript or Dart. However, the majority of developers continue to use and refine their knowledge of JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript and how best to use it is now a central analysis for custom web applications. Much thought was now needed to make sound engineering decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript was now for serious engineers...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Freedom to Live&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mastery leads to freedom from the fear of death, which in turn is the freedom to live. This is sometimes referred to as living in the moment, neither anticipating the future nor regretting the past.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frontend development is now a legitimate software profession. Developers get to choose whether to focus on frontend development or server-side development. No longer is frontend development a nice-to-have with server-side being core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaScript is now the most popular programming language on the planet. But, where do we go from here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I leave to you...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Common Mythic Elements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moongadget.com/origins/myth.html&quot;&gt;common mythic elements&lt;/a&gt; in all monomyths. Here's how JavaScript compares to Star Wars and The Matrix:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Campbell                                                                     &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; Star Wars                                                                                                               &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; The Matrix                                                                          &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt; JavaScript                                                                                         &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Two Worlds (mundane and special)                                             &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Planetside vs. The Death Star                                                                                           &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Reality vs. The Matrix                                                              &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Server-side vs Frontend                                                                            &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The Mentor                                                                   &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Obi-Wan Kenobi                                                                                                          &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Morpheus                                                                            &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Douglas Crockford                                                                                  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The Oracle                                                                   &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Yoda                                                                                                                    &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; The Oracle                                                                          &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; John Resig                                                                                         &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The Prophecy                                                                 &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Luke will overthrow the Emperor                                                                                         &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Morpheus will find (and Trinity will fall for) &quot;The One&quot;                            &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; JavaScript will run everywhere                                                                     &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Failed Hero                                                                  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Biggs                                                                                                                   &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; In an early version of the script, Morpheus once believed that Cypher was &quot;The One&quot; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; MooTools, Prototype                                                                                &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wearing Enemy's Skin                                                         &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Luke and Han wear stormtrooper outfits                                                                                  &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Neo jumps into agent's skin                                                         &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; GWT uses Java to write frontend code                                                               &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Shapeshifter (the Hero isn't sure if he can trust this character)            &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Han Solo                                                                                                                &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Cypher                                                                              &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; CoffeeScript (Designer Languages generally)                                                        &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Animal familiar                                                              &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; R2-D2, Chewbacca                                                                                                        &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; N/A                                                                                 &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; SpiderMonkey                                                                                       &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chasing a lone animal into the enchanted wood (the animal usually gets away) &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Luke follows R2 into the Jundland Wastes; The Millennium Falcon follows a lone TIE fighter into range of the Death Star &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Neo &quot;follows the white rabbit&quot; to the nightclub where he meets Trinity              &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Brendan Eich joins Netscape to create scheme for the browser, where he invents JavaScript instead. &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

</summary>
      <id>http://tiandavis.com/posts/javascript-and-the-monomyth</id>
      <updated>2014-06-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Tian Davis</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Foundation Is Everything</title>
      <link href="http://tiandavis.com/posts/foundation-is-everything" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I remember when I first realized some Universities were no longer teaching Computer Engineering and Computer Science students C++. Realizing the sad truth in it, I cringed. Flushed with sadness, I was utterly sick to my stomach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, I spent my University years watching men do things with C/C++ that would blow your mind today. Granted, these men were utter freaks of nature, and I mean that in a good way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Hercules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of them was a very good friend. I never got to tell him, but sometimes I felt as though he was a best friend. A proverbial programming demi-god since his toddler years, my very best aspirations were to be half as good a developer as he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's call him Hercules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hercules created a welcoming environment where I could explore C++ and literally ask him any questions I wanted. Talk about lucking out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence, OpenGL and Game Theory were Hercules' ideas of a good Friday night. I soaked it all up - osmosis has its place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hercules would always ask, &quot;Did you check the MSDN examples?&quot; That was the back-in-the-day speak for, &quot;Did you Google it?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if impending doom wasn't lurking around the corner, he'd say, &quot;Give it five minutes.&quot; Give it five minutes. That meant learn to sleep on problems - a technique I use almost every single day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For kicks we'd code trivia programs on paper. Or hop on over to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Obfuscated_C_Code_Contest&quot;&gt;International Obfuscated C Code Contest&lt;/a&gt; to checkout the latest entries. C/C++ can be a powerful binding force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, what I learned most from Hercules was less about being a coding BAMF and more about being an effective mentor, teacher and guide. And there isn't a semi-colon in the world I wouldn't write to learn those lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Cerberus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there were the Twins. I affectionately called them &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cerberus&quot;&gt;Cerberus&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title wasn't as glamorous as Hercules. Naturally, they didn't care for it. I understood. It's not like they were guarding anything in particular. Quite the opposite actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, Cerberus shared their knowledge of C++ and object oriented programming freely, albeit not always openly. Picture this...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you met a guy who could code you under the table? I'm talking six feet under the table? Like get ready to pray to whatever God you worship time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now clone this guy. Then imbue each clone with the ability to telepathically share code and communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now your starting to get a clear picture of the coding beast that is Cerberus. Programming Gods? Yes. Productivity Ninjas. OMFGBBQ. Freaks of nature? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now mind you, I was already a pretty accomplished C++ developer under Hercules' apprenticeship - way above my peers - before I started pairing with Cerberus on big projects. Yet, the sheer speed with which Cerberus shipped product continues to haunt me 'til today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time with the Twins, bonded by our shared love for C++, taught me so many things I remain grateful for. Cerberus thought me how to break down domains into understandable and digestible models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They taught me how to find out which code libraries were best and how to realize when it was time for new blood. But, most importantly, my time with Cerberus taught me to ship. And shipping continues to have value beyond measure. Indeed, priceless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Bit by the Software Engineering Bug&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on my first professional grade application with Cerberus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a Flight Management System - aptly code named Krull. Unmanaged and free C++ with an OpenGL and OpenAL core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few rough edges, no doubt, but we knocked the socks off our competition. And right then, right there, I saw the inevitable success that comes from combining competent code with an eye for design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone will be as lucky as I was. Not everyone will have the chance to be mentored by an Olympian and to pair program with the sons of Echidna and Typhon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that's the whole point, isn't it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentals should prepare you for greatness whether you're fighting code with the sons of Olympus or simply trying to meet your project deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C++ is one of those foundations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live it. Breathe it. And you'll be prepared for whatever comes your way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, what do you think the Ruby interpreter is written in? Or the PHP interpreter for that matter? The roots of iOS? Nginx? This stuff isn't magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell, while you're at it, throw the Node.js V8 engine into the mix. And since we're talking Google lineage, checkout Chrome Native Client. All the tools many have come to know and love all have a single language at their core. You guessed it - C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should knowledge so crucial to the many, be vested in so little few? Hell No! The first chance you get to learn C++, do it...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not because I said so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do it because you love open source. Do it because you cherish progress. Do it because, like me, you live and breathe this shit!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://tiandavis.com/posts/foundation-is-everything</id>
      <updated>2012-05-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Tian Davis</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Hustle and Code</title>
      <link href="http://tiandavis.com/posts/hustle-and-code" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slow down. Learn the Fundamentals. And Hustle. Because learning to develop good software takes ten years. A lot of people will disagree with me on this. A lot of big people &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_Basic&quot;&gt;already have&lt;/a&gt; and many of us are still cleaning up that mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ccs.neu.edu/home/matthias/HtDP2e/index.html&quot;&gt;How to Design Programs&lt;/a&gt;, the authors said it well, &quot;Bad programming is easy. &lt;em&gt;Idiots&lt;/em&gt; can learn it in &lt;em&gt;21 days&lt;/em&gt;, even if they are &lt;em&gt;Dummies&lt;/em&gt;.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn't 1991 and the tragedy that was Visual Basic (VB). This isn't a time when the 21 days paradigm turned everyone - from Help Desk Support to Accountants to Managers to Lawyers - into overnight programmers. Yet, still this notion of learn to program overnight lingers more tragically than even The Bard himself could imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why is everyone in such a rush?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://norvig.com/21-days.html&quot;&gt;Teach Yourself Programming in Ten Years&lt;/a&gt;, author Peter Norvig posits the quintessential question in this knowledge arms race, &quot;Why is everyone in such a rush?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bring the point home, Norvig did an Amazon search to see how many book titles promised to teach you something in X amount of days. He received 248 hits. Later he swapped &lt;em&gt;days&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;hours&lt;/em&gt; with similar results at 253 hits. Norvig goes on to note that 96% of the titles returned were computer and programming related. That was 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 2011 and the results are even more astounding. If you want to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/search-handle-url/ix=books&amp;amp;rank=%2Bfeaturedrank&amp;amp;fqp=power%01pubdate%3A%20after%201992%20and%20title%3A%20days%20and%0D%20%28title%3A%20learn%20or%20title%3A%20teach%20yourself%29&amp;amp;sz=25&amp;amp;pg=1/ref=s_b_np&quot;&gt;teach yourself something in X days&lt;/a&gt;, you'll find 950 titles at your disposal. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/search-handle-url/ix=books&amp;amp;rank=%2Bfeaturedrank&amp;amp;fqp=power%01pubdate%3A%20after%201992%20and%20title%3A%20hours%20and%0D%20%28title%3A%20learn%20or%20title%3A%20teach%20yourself%29&amp;amp;sz=25&amp;amp;pg=3/ref=s_b_np&quot;&gt;Swap days with hours&lt;/a&gt; and you'll find 675 titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's 3 to 4 times more titles than just a decade ago. In both cases, programming titles are the the overwhelming majority. In particular, the &lt;em&gt;hours&lt;/em&gt; category has a higher density of computer programming books than the &lt;em&gt;days&lt;/em&gt; category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hours? Learn to program in Hours? You can't learn the necessary fundamentals in hours, nor days. It takes years! It takes Ten Years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Fundamentals - You can't rush good wine!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like good wine, you can't rush good programming. It will take time. You won't learn it in 24 hours. But with passion and purpose and lots and lots of practice, you can get good - really good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don't necessarily have to finish a four-year Computer Engineering or Computer Science program. But you do need drilled, hands-on fundamentals. For everyone, where you get those fundamentals will be - guess what - fundamentally different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, you will be an apprentice to a parent, older sibling or mentor. For others, you might start programming games as a youngling. Still, for others, you will go to University for the fundamentals and if you are lucky, leave before the other nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But each of you will have a different, diverse story and that's Ok! That's the DNA that will shape your decisions and the projects you pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is there are fundamentals in the development game and no matter how you get it, you better have it! You can't rush the fundamentals either - they need time to mature and coarse through your veins. The fundamentals need time to learn you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;You've got to Hustle to get Good!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry to say, but you're not going to get good grinding assignments in a grey cube for eight hours-a-day. Nothing inherently with the color grey stops you either. It's just that mentorship seldom takes place in corporate life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have the opportunity to learn from a master developer in a corporate environment - consider yourself lucky and thank him or her. But most importantly, when it's your turn, pass on what you've learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the other 98% of you, the mentorship isn't coming so you've gotta hustle. You've gotta get out of your comfort zone and work on different teams shipping different types of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You've gotta work for the megalomaniacal failed bed bug researcher turned IT Executive since he can tell a great story and once taught a call girl Excel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You've gotta work for the spoiled rich kid who will make you Director of Technology (or pick your own title) if you promise to work 21 hours a day and hook an intravenous (IV) of Red Bull to your medulla oblongata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You've gotta work for people who's agenda is everything but making good software. It's in those darkest hours that your judgement is intensified. It is in those darkest nights that your character is solidified and your religion hardened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are the times where you'll learn what's right, what's wrong and what needs more time to simmer. Those are the times when you'll get to see the effects of bad architecture and bad design and how that makes your Users feel. Those are the times when you'll learn which decisions make sense and which don't. Those are the times when you'll learn to say, &quot;Hell No!&quot; and mean it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most importantly, those are the times when you'll either learn to take responsibility for the software decisions you make or you'll join the countless many who've decided to never take responsibility for the decisions they make. These are the experiences that make great product designers and you will draw on them time-and-time again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Spartan or Arcadian? Warrior or Brawler?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I see it, you have two choices. Learn from Dummies and be an Arcadian - a brawler at best. Or face your personal Agoge and emerge a Spartan - an Elite Warrior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make the cleanest light saber you want. But you can't be a Jedi until you've faced your Vader. You've gotta hustle! And if you survive, you will have joined the elite and be able to smell bullshit and bad code a mile away - sometimes at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in that time, you'll learn to appreciate Design Patterns, Software Architecture and Modern Object Oriented Design. In that time, you'll learn to love Object Relational Mappers (ORM), Separation of Concerns (SoC) and User Experiences (UX).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming for Dummies won't teach you these - Dummies don't care about these! They care about getting things done the quickest so they can look smarter than you. They don't care about the end User. They don't care about how the software will be installed. They don't even care about how they will maintain the software. But you must!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dummies care about the latest IDE and the latest shiny runtime features. They don't care about the deep mentorship and bonding that comes from Code Reviews and discussing best practices with an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming for Dummies won't teach you to appreciate data integrity or domain modeling. Programming for Dummies won't teach you how to value your software team. You've got to learn to value these precepts on your own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Don't back down - Step up!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don't want to be an Arcadian, you want to be a Spartan. We need you to be a Spartan. And that's not happening in 30 or 21 days. It's not happening in 24 or 12 hours. And it's certainly not going to happen learning from Sams or any other Dummy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can do it! You can learn the proper Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC). You can learn to care about your users and your team. It's a lot to learn and a lot to take in. I know this and I know it can seem like a mountain to climb. But always remember this: &lt;em&gt;It Ain't the Size of the Dog in the Fight, It's the Size of the Fight in the Dog&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's the rush? Slow down. Learn the Fundamentals. And Hustle. Cause learning to develop good software takes ten years. Hustle and Code. Get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://tiandavis.com/posts/hustle-and-code</id>
      <updated>2011-08-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Tian Davis</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Rails 3 and The jQuery Effect</title>
      <link href="http://tiandavis.com/posts/rails-3-and-the-jquery-effect" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ruby on Rails 3.0 was a big evolution of the Rails DNA. Architectural changes were hard to miss - true. But, more happened - more changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Rails 3.0 I saw a strategic change in the way the Rails Core Team viewed itself. Prototype went from being the Official JavaScript framework for Rails to being the Recommended JavaScript framework for Rails. That's a really big deal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That opened the door for JavaScript options when using Rails. And dare I say, it was a venerable extension of diplomacy to the rest of the JavaScript community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The jQuery Effect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There I stood as a Rails developer - proud as ever - because above all this move showed that the Rails Core Team leads. I call this &lt;em&gt;The jQuery Effect&lt;/em&gt; and it's about getting out of the way of progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!--The jQuery Effect--&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;noConflict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;jQuery has built a vibrant community of developers. And dare I say it was this single line of code that turned the tides in the JavaScript Framework Wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The JavaScript Framework Wars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to long ago the JavaScript Framework Wars were armed for battle and at conflict. Who threw the first punch? We'll never know. One thing's for sure, it was on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider these frameworks the major Contenders: Prototype, jQuery, MooTools and Ext JS. As with all Wars the issue is about assets and who owns what. Here, the asset is the infamous dollar ($) sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this over a dollar ($) sign? Yes! Only one framework at a time could use the dollar ($) sign. Since the $() function was an integral part of each of these frameworks, no one wanted to change there use of the dollar ($) sign just to suit &quot;that other framework.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Finding Common Ground&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What John Resig and the jQuery Core Team realized was that people used the $ for efficiency not identity. So let other frameworks use the $ and give jQuery developers the best of both worlds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;html&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;noConflict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;ready&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;#button&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;click&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;alert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Hello World!&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;//document.ready&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As a result jQuery developers didn't have to choose efficiency over flexibility. While the other frameworks pandered, &quot;One Framework to Rule Them ALL.&quot; jQuery played it's hand and moved aside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;One Developer's Story&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;jQuery was young and I was an accomplished Prototype developer. I had my favorite Prototype modal dialog I just had to use for a recent project - I had too. But I also wanted to broaden my horizons and try another framework as my main.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that time, jQuery looked really promising but the plugins were ugly. MooTools had some really beautiful plugins, but the Communinity believed you should only use one JavaScript framework and they weren't budging - I agree with them today ;) Ext JS felt too heavy for me and I passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really liked how polished MooTools plugins were, but chosing MooTools meant I was locked into using MooTools and only MooTools. And as I stated earlier, &quot;I just had to have the Prototype Modal Dialog plugin.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went with jQuery. I went with jQuery because it gave me options. And in a world of uncertainty, options are the currency of progress. With a single line of code, I was able to use jQuery as my foundation and still got to use my &quot;favorite&quot; Prototype Modal Dialog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Aftermath&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that project, I never used that Modal Dialog again! And you know what? Something suprising happened - something I didn't even expect to happen: &lt;em&gt;I never used another JavaScript framework again either.&lt;/em&gt; I was bit by the jQuery bug and I was a convert for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did that happen? How? A single line of code? Really? Yes. &lt;em&gt;jQuery.noConflict();&lt;/em&gt; allowed me to test the framework and not have to choose between some of my favorite plugins and jQuery. It was not an all or nothing transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jQuery team knew its JavaScript framework was great and so it decreased the friction needed to adopt jQuery and let evolution play its course. It was a success! Today jQuery is one of the most popular and widely used JavaScript frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often wonder how many developers converted to jQuery in that fashion. How many picked up jQuery and never looked back because of &lt;em&gt;The jQuery Effect&lt;/em&gt;. We may never know the true numbers, but I'd gamble the numbers would be both shocking and impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Rails 3.1 and jQuery Sitting in a Tree&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Rails 3.0 was released, I believe DHH and the Rails Core Team took a similar stance as the jQuery team did so long ago: Give developers options and get out of the way of progress - let evolution play its course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier today &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/dhh/statuses/45923430608023552&quot;&gt;DHH announced&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rails 3.1 will ship with jQuery as the default JavaScript library. Prototype helpers/RJS are going into a gem.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; DHH (@dhh) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dhh/statuses/45923430608023552&quot;&gt;March 10, 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I believe Ruby on Rails is the most powerful and beautiful web application framework today. If you doubt that, I dare you to look around the ecosystem. You WILL NOT find a single - respectable - web framework, written in any language, that hasn't adopted the paradigms and philosophies of Rails. Not a single one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DHH and the Rails Core Team know Rails is the best framework out there and it is up to them to reduce the friction needed to adopt the framework. With the countless number of developers using jQuery, shipping Rails 3.1 with jQuery is a powerful move indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Lesson&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson here is simple. Reduce the friction between your Product and potential Customer. Make it easy for your customer to access your product. Then the product can stand on its own and wow the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But until you get the product in your customer's hand, what do you have? Nothing. Not even a chance. That's a powerful thing that John Resig and the jQuery Core Team understood well and it paid off big time. First by its adoption my Microsoft and ASP.Net MVC and now by Ruby on Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I commend both the jQuery Core Team and the Rails Core Team. And many thanks for teaching this powerful lesson indeed. I can't wait to get my hands on the Rails 3.1 release.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://tiandavis.com/posts/rails-3-and-the-jquery-effect</id>
      <updated>2011-08-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Tian Davis</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Silly Rabbit, Parsing HTML is for Kids!</title>
      <link href="http://tiandavis.com/posts/silly-rabbit-parsing-html-is-for-kids" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If I had a nickel for every time a developer says, &quot;Don't worry, I'll just whip up a RegEx and parse that HTML in no time.&quot; I'd retire right this very second. I've grown less and less shocked over the years. Still I'm left surprised every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I've been there done that. That's why I know it's generally a bad idea. Given, there are times when you have to suck it up and use a Regular Expression. But experience has shown me that this is rarely one of those times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Red Pill - Do you even have to ask?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it's reading HTML or stripping HTML tags out of user generated content, the feeling is always the same - utter shock!
Talking a developer out of using RegEx to parse HTML is like talking a good friend off the ledge. Curiously, no one ever says, &quot;Hey, let's use RegEx to parse XML!&quot; So what's the deal with HTML? Is it the familiarity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell, even Jon Skeet cannot parse HTML using regular expressions and the last guy to try went &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2009/11/parsing-html-the-cthulhu-way.html&quot;&gt;batshit crazy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is too valuable to start down this path. Spend what little time you have implementing your core requirements and business logic. This is not a fight you need to pursue. Just say no and get back to the primary task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I begin? Where do I even begin? What can I say that hasn't &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1732348/regex-match-open-tags-except-xhtml-self-contained-tags#answer-1732454&quot;&gt;already been said&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I don't know where to begin. The truth is there will be hundreds of scenarios that you didn't or couldn't or will never think about. Maybe even thousands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this boils down to is simple: You will set your project in a never ending cycle of fix-break-fix because chances are there will always be HTML to break your little RegEx parser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don't want that! Believe me, you don't need that! Technical Debt is not something to take on lightly. It's not something to take on at all. But for God's sake, don't take it on to parse HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't take on Technical Debt by rolling your own RegEx HTML parser. Don't do it because the solution is simple - use an HTML parser library. Preferably, one with XPath and CSS3 Selector support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your language and platform, I understand this is easier said than done. But if you can pull it off, the benefits will far far outweigh the thrill of slinging on your mouse and riding into the sunset with your trusty Aeron deluxe chair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I'll do you one better. Instead of just saying, &quot;Grab an HTML Parser.&quot; I'll point out fine HTML Parsers for different platforms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ruby: Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://nokogiri.org/&quot;&gt;Nokogiri&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JavaScript: Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://jquery.com/&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHP: Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.php.net/manual/en/domdocument.loadhtml.php&quot;&gt;PHP5 DOMDocument&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;.Net(C#): Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://htmlagilitypack.codeplex.com/&quot;&gt;Html Agility Pack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VB6: Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codeguru.com/vb/vb_internet/html/article.php/c4815&quot;&gt;MSHTML&lt;/a&gt; - The DOM Parser used in IE&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python: Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://lxml.de/xpathxslt.html&quot;&gt;lxml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perl: Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.cpan.org/~gaas/HTML-Parser-3.68/Parser.pm&quot;&gt;HTML:Parser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java: Try &lt;a href=&quot;http://htmlcleaner.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;HTML Cleaner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There, now all you have to do is get up to speed. Then see if one of these full-fledged HTML Parsers will do the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using an HTML Parser isn't some new bag of tricks either. Don't be surprised to see jQuery-like syntax for some of the more syntactically pleasing libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Toss that cowboy hat out the door&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not about being a Cowboy Coder. You do not have to be a Hero. I'm pretty sure you have a business task to accomplish. And I'm equally sure that task isn't to write an HTML Parser. So don't do it - just say no!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You'll thank yourself in a couple weeks when the Red Bull and adrenaline wears off. It's really not worth it! Granted we all have to start from somewhere. Think of this as your new beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://tiandavis.com/posts/silly-rabbit-parsing-html-is-for-kids</id>
      <updated>2011-04-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Tian Davis</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Object Oriented Ruby: Classes, Mixins and Jedi</title>
      <link href="http://tiandavis.com/posts/object-oriented-ruby-classes-mixins-and-jedi" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Objects, Ruby Classes and Mixins are the topics today. Ruby is a dynamic language with a focus on simplicity and productivity. Object Oriented programming in Ruby is at once elegant and simple. Ready for more power and flexibility? Let's get started...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most academics approach object oriented discussions with Tonka toys and furry kittens. Well, academia can take a backseat. From here on out, dump the Tonka toys and put the kittens to bed - we're talking Lightsabers and Jedi baby!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_xP3fI7yn5s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Objects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An object is an instance of a class. Each instance having its own unique attributes and state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;dojo.rb&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Jedi&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anakin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Jedi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Anakin&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anakin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duel&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anakin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lightsaber&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Ruby&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anakin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;juyo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, the &lt;em&gt;anakin&lt;/em&gt; object is an instance of the Jedi class. Apparently, Anakin is having trouble with some galactic fraktards and fires up his Ruby lightsaber using the &lt;em&gt;lightsaber&lt;/em&gt; method. Then Anakin proceeds to bring the hurt using a lightsaber combat form called &lt;a href=&quot;http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/Lightsaber_combat&quot;&gt;Juyo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the Jedi class is deceivingly simple. That simplicity is possible because of a well designed domain model (collection of ruby classes that model a particular system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I'll take you behind the scenes and show you the techniques you need to write clean, maintainable and awesome Ruby code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Ruby Classes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ruby, an class (object) encapsulates a group of attributes (state) and methods (operations). A developer manipulates an object's state (instance variables) only through class accessors and methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Jedi.rb&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's how a Jedi class might look:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Padawan&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Forms&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Jedi&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Padawan&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Forms&lt;/span&gt;
  
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;initialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Unknown&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Jedi.initialize&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;duel&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Only a Sith deals in absolutes.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Padawan.rb&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Padawan class might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Force&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Lightsaber&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Padawan&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;attr_accessor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:name&lt;/span&gt;
  
      &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Force&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Lightsaber&lt;/span&gt;
  
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;inspect&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Force-Sensitive: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@name&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Padawan would be derived from maybe a &lt;em&gt;Sentient&lt;/em&gt; class. But for simplicity I'm including in the Padawan class attributes you might have seen in a class like &lt;em&gt;Sentient&lt;/em&gt;. For example, the &lt;em&gt;@name&lt;/em&gt; attribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Constructor (Initialization)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initialized method is Ruby's constructor method for class implementations. It's called whenever a new instance of a class is created. For example, here a new instance of the Jedi class is called. The result is the &lt;em&gt;anakin&lt;/em&gt; object:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#dojo.rb&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anakin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Jedi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Anakin&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This example illustrates a beautiful feature of Ruby - &lt;em&gt;Flexible Initialization&lt;/em&gt;. This means you have the option to pass a parameter or not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#Jedi.rb&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;initialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Unknown&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can choose not to pass a parameter. In that case, creating an instance of the Jedi object might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sith&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Jedi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the default value of the &lt;em&gt;@name&lt;/em&gt; attribute would be &lt;em&gt;Unknown&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Inspect&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You've noticed by now that when we try to look at an object directly, we are shown something cryptic like &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;#Jedi:0x101237498 @name=&quot;Anakin&quot;&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. This is just a default behavior, and we are free to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All we need to do is add a method named &lt;em&gt;inspect&lt;/em&gt;. You should return a string that describes the object in some meaningful way - including the states of some or all of its instance attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we return the value of the &lt;em&gt;@name&lt;/em&gt; attribute on the Padawan class. In this instance of the Jedi object, the value of the &lt;em&gt;@name&lt;/em&gt; attribute is Anakin. So I setup the &lt;em&gt;inspect&lt;/em&gt; method to return  &lt;em&gt;Force-Sensitive: Anakin&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;em&gt;irb&lt;/em&gt; from Terminal. Then &lt;em&gt;load 'dojo.rb'&lt;/em&gt;. And type &lt;em&gt;Anakin&lt;/em&gt;. Type &lt;em&gt;Exit&lt;/em&gt; to leave irb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Accessors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A class may have many attributes. It really all depends on the domain you're trying to model. Accessing those attributes directly is not a good practice. Instead, you should create accessors to read and write to those attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish this in some languages is a pain. You would have to define a &lt;em&gt;getter&lt;/em&gt; method and &lt;em&gt;setter&lt;/em&gt; method for each class attribute. Imagine having 10 attributes. That's 20 different accessors you would have to write - in addition to writing your attributes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruby has a more elegant solution - the attr_accessor shortcut:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Padawan&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;attr_accessor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:name&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This gets you the following Ruby class methods for FREE:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#attr_reader&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@name&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#attr_writer&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Awesome! This is at once elegant and beautiful. You can add as much attribute accessors as you like: attr_accessor :name, :weight, :etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You're not going to always want a &lt;em&gt;getter&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;setter&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes you might only need one. You can do that in Ruby:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;attr_reader&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:midi_chlorian&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;attr_writer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:heart_rate&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You get the picture!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Methods&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Methods are how we interact with our Ruby classes. Methods allow us to encapsulate activities specific to the particular class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#Jedi.rb&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;duel&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Only a Sith deals in absolutes.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Methods sometimes perform work on a Ruby classes' attributes. Sometimes a method just performs work specific to the class. In our Jedi class, we have a &lt;em&gt;duel&lt;/em&gt; method. This method is used to convey some Jedi axiom just before battle begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like an initialize constructor, a method can take parameters. A Ruby method can even have a default parameter. So our &lt;em&gt;duel&lt;/em&gt; method could have looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#Jedi.rb&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;duel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;opponent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Sith&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;You disappoint me &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;opponent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Only a Sith deals in absolutes.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Coming from static languages, Ruby's minimalistic approach to object oriented programming is at once refreshing and inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still with me? Great! Let's move on to more advanced topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Inheritance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, you'll reach a situation where different Ruby classes have the same attribute and perform the same basic actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that a Jedi evolved from a Padawan. Therefore, a Jedi should posses the skills of a Padawan with the further developed skills of a Jedi Knight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ruby, such relationships can be expressed using inheritance. Here, the Padawan class is called the parent class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Jedi&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Padawan&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In this way we can reuse the Padawan class for other force-sensitives that we wouldn't consider Jedi. For example, we could have a Sith class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Sith&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Padawan&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Darth Vader was once a Padawan until he turned to the Dark Side and became a Sith Lord. As such, you would expect him to have the knowledge and training of a Padawan with the learning of a Dark Knight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Polymorphism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be cases where certain methods of the parent class will need to be implemented differently in the inheriting class. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Sith&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Padawan&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;inspect&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Peace is a lie. There is only passion. - &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@name&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, the &lt;em&gt;inspect&lt;/em&gt; method from the &lt;em&gt;Sith&lt;/em&gt; class will be used instead of the &lt;em&gt;inspect&lt;/em&gt; method from the &lt;em&gt;Padawan&lt;/em&gt; class. Object oriented languages (like Ruby) that facilitate this type of behavior are said to be polymorphic. Therefore, the above is an example of Polymorphism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than exhaustively define every characteristic of every new class, we only need to redefine the differences between the parent class and the child class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Does Ruby support multiple inheritance?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Ruby was designed with single inheritance. This was on purpose. Single inheritance encourages you to develop a deeper understanding of your domain model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there are times when a domain model could benefit from sharing methods that do not require a full blown class. That's where Ruby Mixins come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Mixins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mixins are Ruby modules. Modules are a collection of methods. You cannot create an instance of a module. Therefore, modules do not maintain state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After requiring a Ruby module, you would then include that module in your Ruby class. This is called a Mixin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Lightsaber&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Padawan&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Lightsaber&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Lightsaber.rb&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the Mixin Lightsaber module:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;module&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;Lightsaber&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;lightsaber&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;crystal&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Jade&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Lightsaber.initialized: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;crystal&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So when I instantiate an instance of the Jedi class, I get access to the Lightsaber module - pure Mixin love:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#dojo.rb&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Jedi&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anakin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Jedi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Anakin&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anakin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lightsaber&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Ruby&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Modules are for sharing behavior (methods), while classes are for modeling relationships between objects. Ruby classes can Mixin a module and receive all its methods for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Active Record - Base Class or Mixin?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might think Active Record should have been included rather than extended by a subclass. You can use your own parent class at that point right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So should Active Record have been implemented as a Mixin instead of a Base Class? Hell No!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying it should is a half-truth at best. What never follows such statements is a disclosure that you will spend exorbitant amounts of time mapping your class attributes to a database DSL (domain specific language).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This behavior really adds up to your detriment when dealing with larger domain models. But this is never said. It's that little gotcha that, not surprisingly, never gets mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe for the best speed, simplicity and maintainability, Active Record is best implemented as a base class that you inherit with a single line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare that to the many lines you will spend to map your class attributes to database types. It really is a no-brainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could stop here, but I believe you'll be able to make better judgments when you have a fuller picture of the issue. So I'm going to tell you when implementing Active Record as a mixin makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense when you're dealing with legacy code that already has a base class coupled with an inefficient, custom data access layer. Then I recommend using a Ruby ORM like &lt;a href=&quot;http://datamapper.org/&quot;&gt;Datamapper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will spend a lot of time wiring up your domain models, but you'll get a mature and flexible data layer - just the type of sprucing up any legacy app could use.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://tiandavis.com/posts/object-oriented-ruby-classes-mixins-and-jedi</id>
      <updated>2011-01-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Tian Davis</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Rails 3.0 rescue from Routing Error Solution</title>
      <link href="http://tiandavis.com/posts/rails-resuce-from-routing-error-solution" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I've got good news and I've got bad news. As of Rails 3.0.1, using rescue_from in your ApplicationController to recover from a routing error is broken! That's the bad news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is I have a solution that will keep you in unison with the Rails Core Team. The Rails team has promised a fix some time in Rails 3.1. Until then, I've got readers and I've got customers and I &lt;em&gt;shudder&lt;/em&gt; at the thought of showing them a generic error page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Situation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's bad enough an error has occurred in the first place. At that point I want to take control of the situation and rescue my audience from a bad experience back to enjoyment!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously in Rails 2.3.8 and below you could handle routing errors elegantly using rescue_from ActionController::RoutingError:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ApplicationController&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;ActionController&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rescue_from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;ActionController&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;RoutingError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:with&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:render_404&lt;/span&gt;
    
      &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;render_404&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;logger&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;info&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Rendering 404: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
          
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;render&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Rails&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;/public/404.html&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:status&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;404&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:layout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, things are a little different in Rails 3. The reality is, as of Rails 3.0.1, ApplicationController can't catch ActionController::RoutingError and thus, we cannot take advantage of rescue_from like we used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, for those of you who don't know, I'm a realist. So, I'm not expecting the Rails team to spring a solution overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I'm going to wait for the Official fix from the Rails Core Team. In the meantime, I need a simple, no side effects solution that I can use right now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Simple Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of those times when it's great to be a developer. There is nothing we can't solve with a little elbow grease and ingenuity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding on the suggestion given by the Rails core team, here's the solution I use to handle routing errors in Rails 3.0:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;config/routes.rb&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code should go to the end of your routes.rb file. That way it will be given the least priority and therefore, act as a wildcard catchall for all those rogue url resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Yourapp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Application&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;routes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;draw&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#Last route in routes.rb&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;match&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;*a&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;errors#routing&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NOTE: The &quot;a&quot; is actually a parameter in the Rails 3 Route Globbing technique. For example, if your url was &lt;em&gt;/this-url-does-not-exist&lt;/em&gt;, then params[:a] equals &quot;&lt;em&gt;/this-url-does-not-exist&lt;/em&gt;&quot;. So be as creative as you'd like handling that rogue route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;app/controllers/errors_controller.rb&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I handle my routing errors. I leverage previous 404 handling code from my original ApplicationController mentioned above. So, my errors_controller.rb looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ErrorsController&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;ApplicationController&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;routing&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;render_404&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, feel free to modify to fit your individual needs. Everyone's situation will be slightly different. For example, if you're not going to reuse your 404 error handling logic, then here's the full ErrorsController without inheritance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;ErrorsController&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;ApplicationController&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;routing&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;render&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Rails&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;/public/404.html&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:status&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;404&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:layout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kp&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I'm big on keeping things simple. I believe solutions should be simple without being simplistic. Like I said earlier, I look forward to an Official solution from the Rails Core Team. Until then, this gets the job done!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I encourage you to dig into Rails 3 and have a little fun. And if you have another solution, post here so we can discuss. Until next time Beloved, take care!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://tiandavis.com/posts/rails-resuce-from-routing-error-solution</id>
      <updated>2010-11-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Tian Davis</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
</feed>
